Guide to the Betty Fussell Papers MSS.160
Fales Library and Special Collections
Betty Fussell Papers
1947-2011
1966-2009
Fales Library and Special Collections
Fussell, Betty Harper
MSS.160
56 Linear Feet in 52 record cartons, 2 manuscript boxes, 2 oversize flat boxes, one flat box, one CD box.
136 audiocassettes 35 audiocassettes, 101 mini audiocassettes
27 videocassettes
12 3.5" floppy disks
16 electronic discs (cd-rom)
7 sound disc (cd)
7 sound discs (minidisc)
4 dvd-r disks
16 Gigabytes 1 USB flash drive
Betty Harper Fussell is an essayist and author of 12 books, including biographies, memoirs, cookbooks, and food histories. Her essays on food, food history, travel, and the arts have appeared in scholarly journals, national magazines and newspapers over the past 40 years. This collection consists of materials related to her food research, lectures, and writings, dating from the mid 20th century to 2012.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Betty Fussell donated the materials from 2005 to 2015. Accession numbers associated with this collection are 2009.160, 2010.160, 2012.160, 2015.160.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Audiovisual materials have not been preserved and may not be available to researchers. Materials not yet digitized will need to have access copies made before they can be used. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact Fales Library with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Arrangement
Materials are arranged at the series level. Series I and II are further arranged to the sub-series level, maintaining original order when evident: Series I, Research and Subject Files Subseries 1, Places Subseries 2, Foods, alphabetized Subseries 3, General notes
Series II, Writings, Interviews, Lectures, Classes Subseries 1, Betty Fussell Books and Related Materials Subseries 2, Betty Fussell Articles, Interviews, Lectures and Classes; Contributions to Works by Others
Series III, Events and Correspondence
Series IV, Media, Graphics, Books
Biographical / Historical
Betty Harper Fussell is an essayist and author of 12 books, including biographies, memoirs, cookbooks, and food histories. She holds bachelor's, master's, and doctoral degrees in English literature. Her essays on food travel and the arts have appeared in scholarly journals, national magazines and newspapers over the past 40 years. She maintains a personal website, https://www.bettyfussell.com.
Related Materials
For more information about Betty Fussell, see her oral history interview in Fales collection MSS 309, Voices from the Food Revolution: People Who Changed The Way Americans Eat. An oral history project conducted by Judith Weinraub.
Scope and Contents
The Betty Fussell Papers consist of materials Fussell created and collected for her research and publications on food history, international cuisines, and cooking. In particular, the collection documents her creation of several cookbooks and food histories focused on US regional foods and specific ingredients, such as corn and beef. The collection contains many interviews with prominent 20th century food writers and chefs, such as James Beard, Craig Claiborne, M. F. K. Fisher, Alice Waters, and Jean-Georges Vongerichten. Materials also chronicle Fussell's evolving sense of her personal identity as a woman, scholar, and food historian of the 20th century. Document types include manuscripts, notes, interview tapes and transcripts, recipes, and correspondence, including handwritten and typed letters, as well as email printouts. The collection also contains unique menus from several international restaurants and works by others, including books, published articles, and newspaper clippings that Fussell collected and arranged by subject.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Advance notice is required for the use of computer records. Original physical digital media is restricted.
Born-digital materials have not been transferred and may not be available to researchers. Researchers may request access copies. To request that material be transferred, or if you are unsure if material has been transferred, please contact The Fales Library & Special Collections (fales.library@nyu.edu) with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Food -- History; Cooking, American |x History |y 20th century; Cookbooks.; Memoirs; Beef.; Corn; Beard, James, 1903-1985; Claiborne, Craig; Vongerichten, Jean-Georges
- Series I: Research and Subject Files
  Scope and Contents
  This series consists of files Fussell created and maintained for her work overall, organized into regional cultures and areas that she visited, foodstuffs, and general notes. It also contains materials from regional events, plus notes, interview transcripts, and drafts of articles about specific places, such as the Spanish olive oil region and California wineries.
  - Places
    - Spain, Cuba, Australia, Kuwait, England,Ireland, 1970-2006 (Box 1)
    - France, 1962-2008 (Box 2)
    - Versailles, China, Bahia, Indonesia, Jordan, Ireland, 1959-2000 (Box 3)
    - Southwest United States, Mexico, South America, California, Kentucky, 1979-2003 (Box 4)
    - SE Asia, Singapore, Bangkok, Hong Kong, Shanghai, 1998-2001 (Box 5)
    - Wisconsin, Peru, 1979-1990 (Box 6)
  - Foods
    - Foods, Alphabetized, Beans-Garlic, 1959-1997 (Box 7)
    - Foods, Alphabetized, Grains - Sea Vegetables, 1955-1995 (Box 8)
  - General Notes and Background Materials
    - General Notes, part 1 of 2: food codes, quotations, nutrition, menus, NYU food seminar, 1969-1997 (Box 9)
    - General Notes, part 2 of 2: recipes, restaurants, French food, food arts, 1970-2008 (Box 10)
    - General Notes: Preserves - Wine, New Produce, Recipe Lists, Catalogs, Bibliographies, Food Facts, 1960-2000 (Box 11)
    - Food Issues, Sustainability, Genetically Modified Foods, 1992-2006 (Box 12)
    - Food Publications, 1985-2008 (Box 13)
    - Note Cards on Eating Habits, French Cuisine, Food History, 1965-1970 (Box 14)
- Series II: Writings, Interviews, Lectures, Classes
  This series consists of research, background, and production files, plus drafts Fussell created for books and articles she wrote. Much overlap exists, as articles were expanded into books, and books would lead to lectures and conference talks.
  - Betty Fussell Books and Related Materials
    - Corn Book Notes, 1974-1996 (Box 15)
    - Corn Book Permissions, 1985-1992 (Box 16)
    - Corn Book Research, 1978-1995 (Box 17, Box 18, Box 19)
    - Corn Seeds, Seed Types, 1932-1998 (Box 20)
    - The Story of Corn and Crazy for Corn, 1990-2000 (Box 21)
    - Corn Book Lectures, Promotions, 1990-1998 (Box 22, Folder 12-16)
    - MFK Fisher Interviews, I Hear America Cooking Photos, Background on Regional U.S. cuisine, New England - Southwest, 1967-1989 (Box 23)
    - America Entertains, Masters of American Cookery, Craig Claiborne, James Beard Julia Child, correspondence, 1965-1993 (Box 24)
    - James Beard, 1974-2003 (Box 25)
    - I Hear America Cooking: Masters, 1977-2004 (Box 26)
    - My Kitchen Wars, 1994-2005 (Box 27)
    - Beef Book background research, 1986-2007 (Box 22, Folder 1-11)
    - Animal Industry, 1976-2008 (Box 28)
    - Rancher Interviews, Grassland, Land Use, Buffalo, California, Oregon, Quivira, 1992-2007 (Box 29)
    - Rancher Interviews, Heritage Breeds, Steakhouses, Beef Industry, 1996-2010 (Box 30)
    - National Cattlemen's Beef Association, Texas, Ranchers, Rendering, "Greenies and Myths", 1996-2008 (Box 31)
    - Beef Notes, Talks, Statistics, Recipes, 2002-2012 (Box 32, Folder 10-23)
  - Betty Fussell Articles, Interviews, Lectures and Classes; Contributions to Works by Others
    - Published Articles and Manuscripts, 1973-2008 (Box 33)
    - Published articles arranged chronologically, journal articles, bibliographies, contracts, proposals, 1955-2012 (Box 34)
    - Published Articles, 1955-2005 (Box 35)
    - Story Ideas, Article Drafts, Background Materials, 1965-2006 (Box 36)
    - Food Organization Conferences, Interviews, Book Reviews, 1978-2000 (Box 37)
    - Research and Drafts for Novel, Foie Gras, Magazine Articles, 1976-2007 (Box 38)
    - Joy of Cooking, revised edition, 1994-1997 (Box 39)
    - Jean-Georges Vongerichten profile, Lears articles, 1986-2000 (Box 40)
    - My Kitchen Wars performance, televised appearances, food articles, NYU Food Colloquium, background materials, 1984-2006 (Box 41)
    - Food History Classes, Bread Article, 1994-2003 (Box 42)
    - Corn Lectures, Promos, Classes, 1990-2004 (Box 43)
    - Betty H. Fussell Lectures, 1986-2007 (Box 44)
    - Interviews and Notes on Beef and Related Topics, 2002-2007 (Box 45)
- Series III: Events and Correspondence
  This series consists of materials related to workshops, conferences, classes, and other events Fussell attended, addressed, or led. It also contains some correspondence.
  - California: COPIA Symposium, Greystone Conference, Chalk Hill Winery book draft, 1996-2006 (Box 46)
  - Food Conferences, 1991-2007 (Box 47, Box 48)
  - Food Panels, Presentations, Conferences, Lectures, 1998-2008 (Box 49, Folder 1-10)
  - Correspondence, 1982-1997 (Box 49, Folder 11-14, Box 32, Folder 1-8)
  - Food Events, Interviews, Ephemera, 1966-2008 (Box 50)
- Series IV: Media, Graphics, Books
  This series consists of photographs, negatives, and slides, plus audiovisual, digital, and graphic materials Fussell created and collected for her research, travel, and writings. It also includes books by others, which Fussell collected and consulted.
  - Menus, 1958-1997 (Box 51)
  - Posters and Menus (Box 52)
  - Slides, photographs, graphics of corn and other foods, regions cookbooks, kitchen history, 1970-2003 (Box 53)
  - Slides, 1991-1999 (Box 32, Folder 9)
  - Photographs: Western United States and Vermont; Slides, 1985-2006 (Box 54)
  - Videos and Audiocassettes, 1981-2000 (Box 55)
  - Interviews, minicassettes, 1980-2000 (Box 56)
  - Compact disks, floppy disks, UBS flash drive, 1980-2006 (Box 57)
  - The Niman Ranch Cookbook, 2005 (Box 35)
  - Becoming Native to this Place, 1994 (Box 54)
  - Alimentum: The Literature of Food, Issue 13, 2012 (Box 14)
  - Jean-George: Cooking at Home with a Four-Star Chef, 1998 (Box 14)
  - Simple Cuisine: the Easy, New Approach to Four-Star Cooking, 1990 (Box 14)
  - The Four Seasons: A History of America's Premier Restaurant, 1999 (Box 14)
  - Zapotec, 1954 (Box 28)
  - Last Chance to Eat: the Fate of Taste in a Fast Food World, 2004 (Box 28)
  - When Jesus Came, the Corn Mothers Went Away. Marriage, Sexuality, and Power in New Mexico, 1500-1846, 1991 (Box 28)
  - Writing at the Kitchen Table: the authorized biography of Elizabeth David, 2000 (Box 28)
  - Corn and Corn Growing, 1949 (Box 28)
  - Corn Huskers' Battle of the Bangboards, 1975 (Box 28)
  - Wild Wealth, 1971 (Box 39)